<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
        <title>Scholarly Markdown</title>
        <description>Scholarly Markdown - </description>
        <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/rss.xml</link>
        <link>http:/www.scholmd.org</link>
        <lastBuildDate>2014-07-22T08:26:37+00:00</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>2014-07-22T08:26:37+00:00</pubDate>
        <ttl>1800</ttl>


        <item>
                <title>Workshop June 2013</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Martin Fenner and Stian Haklev organized a one day &lt;em&gt;Markdown for Science&lt;/em&gt; workshop at the Public Library of Science HQ in San Francisco on June 8th, 2013.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you attended, please list yourself on [[people-attending]] with a bit about yourself, and your ideas/wishes for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please add to these two pages: * &lt;a href=&quot;later%20we%20can%20clean%20this%20up%20and%20put%20some%20of%20it%20into%20[[Tools%20to%20support%20your%20markdown%20authoring]]&quot;&gt;[Tools and projects]&lt;/a&gt; * [[Scenarios, barriers to adoption, needs]]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the potential outcomes of the workshop include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Todo list from workshop]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Signs that MD is successing]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Barriers]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[What is Markdown]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes from discussion about the suitability of Markdown for scientific authoring (different stages, disciplines, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comprehensive list of tools/initiatives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes from discussion about collaboration/synergy between tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of interesting examples/showcase (GH repositories etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of “barriers”, “obstacles” etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes from discussion about way forward, applying for grants, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please add your ideas below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;css-styles&quot;&gt;CSS Styles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;swcarpentry&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;swcarpentry&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;(https://twitter.com/swcarpentry/status/332215002675150850)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;_inundata&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;_inundata&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; If you can make it easy (really easy) to add CSS styles to &lt;code&gt;pre&lt;/code&gt; blocks in Markdown, you’ll be my new best friend…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Use case is adding &amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;highlight&amp;quot;&amp;gt; or &amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;comment&amp;quot;&amp;gt; inside an indented block that triggers &amp;lt;pre&amp;gt;.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mix-markdown-with-latex&quot;&gt;Mix Markdown with LaTeX&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paul Groth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to say is that I like how authorea.com lets you mix and match markdown with latex. So a couple things to think about: * how do I transition from markdown to latex (do I want to?) &amp;gt; Mix and match. Write the easy stuff in Markdown and if you are used to writing tables in Latex then stick to Latex for tables. In the near future, on Authorea we could offer an automatic conversion between the two, so you could select a paragraph, click convert to markdown, and you are good to go. For the time being, you can write in Markdown and then convert the entire document to Latex, for example. Although this is still rough around the edges, it is a step in the right direction. Overall, we prefer to impose limitations on what users can do so that we can guarantee them a minimum level of conversion between MD and LaTex. In other words, if we start supporting crazy complicated tables with mini pages, multicolumn, and other (unnecessary imho) Latex environments, we will make it hard/impossible for that content to be displayed in HTML5 and then converted to MD. But, if users write more regular, simpler tables, conversion between the two (or 2+) formats can be guaranteed. So, imposing limitations is the key, we think. FYI we use Pandoc to convert between formats. - Response from Alberto and Nate, creators of Authorea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you deal with style files? &amp;gt; When exporting to pdf we convert markdown to latex and the style file is handled naturally. Online we have our own look. If we wanted to offer authorea as a platform for journals (create-&amp;gt;publish under a different name, ie not authorea but journal x), we could also allow custom css files. - Response from Alberto and Nate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;standard-additional-markup&quot;&gt;Standard additional markup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Philip Lord&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be good to have some discussion on additional markup that might be needed for science. For example, I use [cite]doi://10.1000/1.1.1.1[/cite] or [author]Phillip Lord[/author] to define the author, within my wordpress plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be nice to have some commonality both in the syntax (for example, “shortcodes” as I have used here) and the vocabulary. Ideally, something that will work in Markdown, but also non-markdown text syntaxes or even in word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Authorea we support citations, references, labels, and other Latex-native features in Markdown. We are still not sure which way scientists want to go. At the moment, if you are writing a Markdown doc you still cite using . Maybe sticking with the standard latex format is good enough for most of our users, maybe there would be a more concise syntax. We are not sure. - Response from Alberto and Nate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relying on LaTeX markup for features we see as essential for Scholarly Markdown is a non-starter if the aim is to move beyond just the PDF/dead wood publishing model. We’d certainly want some form of extended MD markup and a processor to write to HTML for example as well as to LaTeX, but also to one or more of the HTML-based slide stacks. - Gavin Simpson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sweet-spot-for-markdown-in-scholarly-communication&quot;&gt;The sweet spot for markdown in scholarly communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karthik Ram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown’s greatest appeal is its simplicity. Adding features to support more complex use cases could be very counterproductive and we would worse off than just using &lt;code&gt;LaTeX&lt;/code&gt;. So what are some of the key features we would need to implement to make markdown a standard tool for scholarly communication? Might be worth spending some time generating such a list and possibly build some prototypes time permitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;flavors-is-great-for-ice-cream-but-not-markdown&quot;&gt;31 flavors is great for ice cream but not markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karthik Ram&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many flavors of markdown at this time. Creating yet another one does not really help. Could we look through existing implementations and identify key features that facilitate scholarly use? For e.g. GitHub has its own non-standard flavor but some of their features are perfect for use in peer-review. Could we combine useful features into a scholarly markdown flavor (ok 32 is not so bad because this one is going to be the best).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no flavor of markdown out there now that is fully sufficient for scholarly publication. At Authorea we use Github flavored MD with some ad-hoc extensions for references, labels etc. These are all plain Latex extensions (i.e., we allow some Latex in MD). By all means, extension of MD will be necessary for science articles. And some of the extensions for science will not be useful for other uses of MD, most likely. - Response from Alberto and Nate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Martin Fenner&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will it take for a critical mass of researchers to use markdown for authoring? I think the biggest challenge is usability - most researchers aren’t interested in learning a markup language. We therefore need nice WYSIWYG editors along the lines of Google Docs, that it is markdown (and git) underneath should matter only for the technical implementation and a small group of geeks. The other challenge is features, but here users may be much more forgiving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible outcome of the workshop for me is that we are better off using the existing tools from LaTeX to online editors working directly with HTML5, and that markdown doesn’t really fill a need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;workgroup-editing-tools&quot;&gt;Workgroup: Editing Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our notes are [[here|Editing-Tools]].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point about hiding MD behind a GUI diminishing the point of using MD in the first place is well made and we’d do well to remember this as work progresses. I like the interface of a Linux app, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.midnightcoding.org/projects/gummi&quot;&gt;Gummi&lt;/a&gt;, that has a split screen interface with an editor window for LaTeX on the left and a preview of the rendered PDF on the right. As you update the code in the left pane, the document is recompiled and shown on the right. This strikes the right balance for me in having readable code with instant gratification. I suspect Gummi could be adapted right now to build MD files by use of a custom build process (via rubber or similar) - we’d only be missing the highlighting for MD syntax in the editor. - Gavin Simpson (&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;ucfagls&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;ucfagls&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;(https://twitter.com/ucfagls))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event is supported by a 1K Force11 Challenge prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please contact the organizers&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;houshuang&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;houshuang&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;(https://twitter.com/&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;houshuang&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;houshuang&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;) and &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;mfenner&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;mfenner&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;(https://twitter.com/&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;mfenner&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;mfenner&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;) if you want to give a presentation or demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/workshop/workshop.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/workshop/workshop</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Extending Markdown</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a lightweight format that does not offer built-in facilities for extension. Instead it is recommended to combine external templating tools to adapt the syntax to particular use cases, where necessary. To avoid an unnecessary inflation in the number of markdown flavors out there, it is recommended that language extensions are used sparingly.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;templating&quot;&gt;Templating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, a good strategy for extending markdown is to place custom markup inside easy to recognize delimiters. When processing the document, &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; run external filters/templating tools on the source document to convert custom markup to HTML (provided HTML is the intended output format) and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; apply the markdown processor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some templating tools available for this purpose are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dexy.it/&quot;&gt;Dexy&lt;/a&gt; filters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jinja.pocoo.org/&quot;&gt;Jinja&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tinlizzie.org/ometa/&quot;&gt;OMeta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;regular expressions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;others…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some good choices for delimiters are: * Double braces &lt;code&gt;. * Backticks, with a prefix inside the backticks. For example,&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;r content&lt;/code&gt; ``. * others… ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this is just a beginning. It would be helpful to have more detailed guidelines for templating and extensions. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Templating needs are different in static (dexy, jinja) vs. dynamic (IPython notebook, rNotebook) use cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a standard way to protect the output of a templating engine from being garbled by the markdown processor? According to Daring Fireball, markdown processors are supposed to ignore the content of block level HTML tags. Is this the common practice of most markdown processors today? Does this mean that only known HTML tags are ignored or any XML-style tag? Is the content of these tags expected to be well-formed XML to parse correctly? …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-notes&quot;&gt;Further Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IPython notebook: no way to reference variables from code in the text (i.e. embed their actual values)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dexy does something like this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; (for &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;) does this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;probably can’t extend to get this to work in a generic setting, but could define a generic syntax?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issues regarding templating, delimeters and parsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where is the information coming from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where does the processing happen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What information can you put in a single file format?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tradeoff between flexibility/ease of use and ability to be precise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t want to get too complicated&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Composable tools/plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python Markdown has extension guidelines&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want online resources for collaborating about Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;documentation regarding different flavors of Markdown (where are they the same, how do they differ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ana: can set something like this up in dexy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/advanced_formatting/extending-markdown.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/advanced_formatting/extending-markdown</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Math</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mathml-the-html-for-math&quot;&gt;MathML the “HTML for math”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web (HTML5), ebook (epub3) and publishing (XML) standard for mathematical equations is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MathML&quot;&gt;MathML&lt;/a&gt;. Just like HTML, MathML can be highly verbose, so manual input is usually done using other tools. In particular, there are several serial math input formats (see below).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many markdown parser tolerate HTML fragments, so MathML fragment can be used when manual input languages are not sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;serialized-math-syntax&quot;&gt;Serialized math syntax&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is usually combined with the most established ones: &lt;strong&gt;LaTeX-like&lt;/strong&gt; syntax (preferrably compatible with MathJax) and &lt;strong&gt;ASCIImath&lt;/strong&gt; syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;latex-like&quot;&gt;LaTeX-like&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most frequently used syntax can be described as “LaTeX-like”. Using LaTeX syntax for math notation has many advantages, the biggest is the number of tools available for LaTeX. This makes it the most versatile syntax for conversion into other formats (MS Word via MathML, PDF via LaTeX, HTML using MathJax).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For HTML output, the most frequently used tool is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathjax.org&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt;, an open source javascript library that can render LaTeX, ASCIImath, and MathML in all browsers. For a list of LaTeX commands that work with MathJax, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.mathjax.org/en/latest/tex.html&quot;&gt;MathJax documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;asciimath&quot;&gt;ASCIImath&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.chapman.edu/~jipsen/mathml/asciimath.html&quot;&gt;ASCIImath&lt;/a&gt; is simpler (and less powerful) as a syntax. It is designed to be converted to MathML and is supported by &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.mathjax.org/en/latest/asciimath.html&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;jqmath&quot;&gt;jqMath&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option is &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathscribe.com/author/jqmath.html&quot;&gt;jqmath&lt;/a&gt;, which is designed as a serialization of MathML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conversion&quot;&gt;Conversion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the conversion process from markdown to other formats, the following options are most frequent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nothing special.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depending on the markdown converter this can work well or be disastrous. Especially “classic” mardkown parsers will interpret every backslash as an escape character and render LaTeX syntax useless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leaving the input untouched&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some parsers like pandoc have added extensions which identify math delimiters (usually &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt;) and treat the content between delimiters as verbatim text – leaving the correct rendering to other tools such as MathJax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;converting equations to MathML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;converting equations to images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/math.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/math</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Figures</title>
                <description>&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TODO&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/figures.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/figures</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Tables</title>
                <description>&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TODO&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;related-posts&quot;&gt;Related posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://inundata.org/2012/12/25/formatting-tables-in-markdown/&quot;&gt;Formatting tables in markdown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/tables.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/tables</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Citations</title>
                <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;citations-breakout-group-at-markdown-for-science-workshop&quot;&gt;Citations breakout group at Markdown for Science workshop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citations should be specified as citation keys (e.g. &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;smith2010&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;smith2010&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. Pandoc and Multimarkdown both support human-readable formatting for this, but use different formatting.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;we-identified-two-use-cases&quot;&gt;We identified two use cases:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fragment of a scientific document&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complete document, e.g. manuscript for paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reference information should be stored in an external bibtex file, which could be referenced by a link or be in the same folder as the markdown file, specified in the metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citation styles should be processed using Citeproc and the Citation Style Language. Citation style can optionally be specified in the metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;questions-from-the-audience&quot;&gt;Questions from the audience :)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stian: Is there any good online collaborative citation manager that supports citekeys (defining/seeing)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;citation-discussion-at-gobbledygook-blog&quot;&gt;Citation discussion at Gobbledygook Blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.martinfenner.org/2013/06/19/citations-in-scholarly-markdown/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, and a very good discussion clarified many issues around citations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;rethink-current-practices&quot;&gt;Rethink current practices&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the things we currently with citations come from a time when journal articles were printed on paper. Examples include citation styles and reference lists. Moving forward we should rethink these practices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citation styles should not be the concern of the author. There is no place for citation styles, or citation formatted with a particular citation style in a markdown document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference lists often don’t make sense for digital documents. What we rather need are good inline links, plus references in a computer-readable format (e.g. bibtex). One challenge with reference lists is the synchronization between inline citations and the reference list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separate files for references create unnecessary overhead and can lead to vendor lock-in. Ideally all the required information should be stored in the markdown document. We should rather export the references from the markdown file to bibtex when transforming to HTML or other output formats (see above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;suggested-approach&quot;&gt;Suggested approach&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citations are links. Thinking of citations as links makes the workflow much easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use reference-style links for documents with many citations. This makes it easier to manage the citations, e.g. when the same paper is cited more than once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use citation keys with reference-style links, and this makes it easy to integrate with reference managers (Papers for example supports &lt;code&gt;[#key][]&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the “title” attribute with reference-style links, using the citation title. DOIs (and often also weblinks) are not human-readable. Using the title makes citations easier to remember and prevents transcription errors (i.e. typos in DOIs or URLs):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[#Beyer2013]: http://dx.doi.org/ 10.1093/annonc/mds579 &amp;quot;Maintaining success, reducing treatment burden,
focusing on survivorship: highlights from the third European consensus conference on diagnosis and
treatment of germ-cell cancer.&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The transformation from markdown into a presentation format (e.g. HTML or PDF) should include link checking (see proof of concept tools below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should support internal links to tables and figures, using anchors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we handle citations that can’t be linked to digital resources? Two ideas are footnotes and placeholder hyperlinks (and &lt;a&gt; tag without href, new in HTML5).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;todo&quot;&gt;Todo&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proof of concept tool that transform links in markdown documents into references, e.g. by pulling information from CrossRef or DataCite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proof of concept tool to display reference information on hover in HTML documents created from markdown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proof of concept tool that extracts all links from a markdown document and generates both a bibliography and bibtex file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best practices how citation information can be stored in HTML link. Probably involves data- attributes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;citation-styles&quot;&gt;Citation Styles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference-manager-support-for-workflow-above&quot;&gt;Reference Manager support for workflow above&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Papers. Allows copy/paste of citekey in different formats (including MMD, Pandoc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mendeley. Copy/paste of citekey in LaTeX format. Allows custom citekeys. Can automatically sync with bibtex file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zotero. ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Endnote. ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;downloading-styles&quot;&gt;Downloading styles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This repo contains citation styles for most journals. Download a copy of the repo somewhere locally by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone git://github.com/citation-style-language/styles.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/citations.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/markdown_elements/citations</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Tools to Support Your Markdown Authoring</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Markdown is automatically rendered to html GitHub but can easily be parsed into a variety of other formats including PDF and LaTex. To convert seamlessly to these formats, you’ll need a document converter. &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; is one such open source tool that is available on all platforms. You’ll need to install a local copy to be able to run all the examples in this repo.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pandoc&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; is a universal document converter. It works from the command line and you can quickly convert a document between any two formats. These include nearly all formats commonly used for scientific writing such as Word, Markdown, Latex, HTML and RTF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/installing.html&quot;&gt;Download and install pandoc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;standalone-applications&quot;&gt;Standalone applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;texts&quot;&gt;Texts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texts.io&quot;&gt;Texts&lt;/a&gt; is rich editor for Markdown, with multiple export options (e.g. PDF, Microsoft Word, LaTeX, HTML, ePub).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;byword&quot;&gt;ByWord&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bywordapp.com&quot;&gt;ByWord&lt;/a&gt; is a simple text editor for OS X and iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;mou&quot;&gt;Mou&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mouapp.com&quot;&gt;Mou&lt;/a&gt; is a simple, free, and powerful Markdown editor/previewer for OS X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;markdownpad&quot;&gt;MarkdownPad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markdownpad.com/&quot;&gt;MarkdownPad&lt;/a&gt; is a Markdown editor for Windows. Both a Free and a Pro version exist; the latter adds support for (amongst other things) GitHub Flavored Markdown and Markdown Extra (including Tables).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;multimarkdown-composer&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown Composer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;http://multimarkdown.com&quot;&gt;MultiMarkdown Composer&lt;/a&gt; is a text editor for Mac that is designed from the ground up around the MultiMarkdown Syntax. It is designed to make writing in MultiMarkdown (or Markdown) even easier than it already is, with automatic syntax highlighting, built in previews, easy export to any format that is supported by MultiMarkdown, and more!” [http://multimarkdown.com].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;retext&quot;&gt;ReText&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/p/retext/home/ReText/&quot;&gt;ReText&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source, platform-independent editor for both Markdown and reStructuredText.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;qute&quot;&gt;Qute&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fbreuer/qute&quot;&gt;Qute&lt;/a&gt;, is an open source, platform-independent editor for Markdown with MathJax-integrated live-preview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;erato&quot;&gt;Erato&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://9muses.se/erato/&quot;&gt;Erato&lt;/a&gt; is a markdown editor for Mac users, supporting Github-flavored Markdown, including YAML front matter and task lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-based-applications&quot;&gt;Web-based applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;draft&quot;&gt;Draft&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://draftin.com&quot;&gt;Draft&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based markdown editor with cloud sync, image hosting and analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;markable&quot;&gt;Markable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markable.in/&quot;&gt;Markable&lt;/a&gt; is another web-based markdown editor with export and integration options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;prose.io&quot;&gt;Prose.io&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://prose.io&quot;&gt;Prose&lt;/a&gt; is a web-based markdown editor for Github Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;previewers&quot;&gt;Previewers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;marked&quot;&gt;Marked&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markedapp.com&quot;&gt;Marked&lt;/a&gt; is a markdown previewer for OS X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/tools-to-support-your-markdown-authoring.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/tools-to-support-your-markdown-authoring</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Learn Markdown in 3 Minutes</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Markdown syntax is extremely simple and you can learn all you need to know within a few minutes.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;formatting-headings&quot;&gt;Formatting headings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# First level
## Second Level
### Third level
#### Fourth level
##### Fifth level
###### Sixth level&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bold-and-italics&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bold&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Italics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bold: **some text**

Italics:  _some other text_

Also italics: *this is also italics*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[link text](link)
example: [click here for a web page](http://google.com)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;figures-and-images&quot;&gt;Figures and Images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figures are formatted the same as links but just add a &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; before the square bracked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;![text description](/path/to/image)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a picture with a link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[![text description](/path/to/image)](http://twitter.com)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;horizontal-lines&quot;&gt;Horizontal lines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;***

or

---&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-and-verbatim&quot;&gt;Code and verbatim&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Inline code: `some code`

Code block:

    some code
    and another line of code
    some more code
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subscript (Pandoc only)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;R~0~&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superscript (Pandoc only)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x^2^&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s most of the formatting you’ll need to get by. I’ll get into citation and table formatting on a separate page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/learn-markdown-in-3-minutes.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/learn-markdown-in-3-minutes</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>What is Scholarly Markdown</title>
                <description>&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markdown that supports the requirements of scientific texts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markdown as format that glues open scientific text resources together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reference implementation with documentation and tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A hashtag: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23scholmd&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#scholmd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/what-is-scholarly-markdown.html</link>
                <guid>http:/www.scholmd.org/basic_setup/what-is-scholarly-markdown</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
        </item>


</channel>
</rss>
